"Why Don't Health Insurers
Encourage Healthier Eating?"
Many of the diseases that
cause a constant drain
on health care budgets can be
prevented by proper nutrition.
So why aren't the big
payors getting involved?
I mean, even like a 1% decline
in excess body fat could
alone save tens of billions.
You'd think at least the health
insurance industry would try
to get people to eat healthier
to try to pay out less money.
Well, one could say the insurance
industry actually benefits from
high health care costs because
these rising costs are simply
passed on to both individuals
and employers in terms of
higher premiums, and
insurers take a fixed percentage
of these premiums
as increasing profits.
They get a piece of the pie,
so the bigger the pie —
the unhealthier everyone is —
the bigger their piece.
As such, insurers have not
done as much as they could
to help reduce health care
costs because lower costs
would hurt their bottom line.
What if there was a medication
that could successfully treat
and even reverse heart disease,
type 2 diabetes, high blood pressure,
and many other chronic conditions
without any negative side effects and
offered the promise of dramatically
reduced health care costs?
Imagine all the advertising
there would be to promote it.
Imagine how much
they would charge.
A drug that could not just
treat but cure diabetes
and these other diseases?
Then what if you were told
that medication exists today,
is available to everyone in
unlimited quantities at a low cost,
but the vast majority of the American
public has never heard about it.
You want a solution to significantly
reduce health care costs?
The solution is to use food
as medical treatment,
specifically foods made from
minimally processed plants.
One of the main barriers is simply
the current widespread belief
that once someone has
a chronic condition,
such as heart disease,
type 2 diabetes,
there's very little that can be done
to actually reverse the disease,
and the best outcome possible
is to maintain the condition
so that it just
doesn't get any worse.
The fact that a whole food
plant-based approach provides
a safe, effective, low-cost alternative
to not just eliminating symptoms
but potentially reversing
the underlying condition
without drugs or surgery
is unknown to a vast
majority of Americans.
In contrast to the pharmaceutical
industry that spends large sums
to market new drugs, there are
not big profits in promoting
a plant-based diet.
The politics surrounding healthcare
is who's going to pay for it,
instead of what kind
of healthcare is best?
And the evidence is overwhelming
that a whole food, plant-based diet
provides the best opportunity to not
only reduce the growth in spending,
but actually decrease total health
care costs more than any drug,
medical procedure, insurance reform,
or provider payment model out there.
Thankfully, the word is spreading.
A review of the evidence published
in Kaiser Permanente's journal
concluded that physicians should
consider recommending
a plant-based diet to all their
patients, especially those
with high blood pressure, diabetes,
cardiovascular disease, or obesity.
Kaiser has followed up
with user friendly guides
(freely available online)
for both physicians and patients,
explaining the benefits
and practical aspects of
implementing a plant-based diet.
So hey, why aren't all insurers
sending out such information
to all their members?
You know how all the
drug ads are like,
"Ask your doctor if this
drug is right for you."
Well, members could be
prompted to ask their physicians
about the ability of plant-based
diets to reduce or eliminate
prescription drug use,
reverse disease.
Though, of course, these
materials would also have
to list all the side effects.
Side effects include
increased energy, lower blood
pressure, improved digestion,
all while eating unlimited
quantities of satisfying food.
Ask your doctor if
plants are right for you.